And this one.
还有这个
Bro
兄弟
You rock!
牛啊
You're just a freshman,
你这才刚大一
and you've completed
已经把哥们我
my ultimate goal
四年的终极目标
for all these four years in college.
全给完成了
It seems that I've achieved
刚开学立的目标
my goals set up at the beginning of college.
好像都完成了吧
Do you plan to
那你还有没有想
do anything else?
干点别的
I haven't decided yet.
没想好
OK, take your time.
没想好那就慢慢想
Let's play for a while.
玩会儿
Go, go, go.
走走走
Let's go. Let's go.
快 走了走了
I can't.
我不会
Hammer him!
锤他
Ma Nan
马楠
Why didn't you
你今天的学校招聘会
attend school's job fair today?
你咋没去啊
Do you still have
你这学期
any classes to retake this semester?
是不是还有课要重修
Ma Nan
马楠
I heard that you got six courses to retake
听说你六门重修
and didn't pass CET-4.
四级没考
It would be difficult for you to graduate.
毕业难喽
Maybe you can ask Li for help.
你不如求求老李呀
Anyhow, he thought highly of you.
他之前挺器重你的
Do you still remember
你还记得你
what you looked like when you were a freshman?
大一时候的样子吗
What have you done in the past three years?
这三年你都干嘛去了
You dropped from the top to the bottom in grade.
从年级第一到倒数第一
Even meteorites
这陨石都没有你
don't fall as fast as you.
坠落得快呀
Only a pure person,
必须是纯粹的人
completely pure,
单纯的人
with a firm will like the sun
意志坚定如太阳
and a burning heart like the volcano,
内心灼热如火山
can not
这样
be devoured by Ma Nan.
才不会被马楠所吞噬
How could there be such a person?
怎么会有这样的人
Oh, students.
哎呀 同学们
You're running, too.
你们也在跑步啊
Ah.
哎呀
Being young is great.
年轻真好啊
Hey.
哎
Don't be shy.
不要害羞嘛
Let's have a running competition.
咱们来一场竞赛吧
I'll come after you.
我来追你们
Hello, Ma Nan.
马楠同学你好
I'm...
我叫
Nan Bei told me about you.
南北跟我说过你
The coach of
二队的
team two, right?
教练是吧
Sa
小撒
Just say what you want.
你有什么就直说吧
My name's Sa Jixue.
我叫撒季学
Alright,
那好 这样
then I'll get straight to the point.
我就开门见山了
OK.
好
The reason why I asked you to come here
这次请你来呢
is that I hope you can join
就是希望你能
our school's debate team.
加入我们校辩论队
Team two.
二队的
No.
不加
Ma Nan, you have to believe
马楠同学你要相信
that I have a careful plan
对于二队未来的发展
for the future development
我是有一个
of team two.
周密的计划的
In the future,
在未来
we will enter the provincial competition, beat the team one,
杀入省赛 击败一队
and reach the national peak.
走向全国巅峰
These are all just around the corner.
那都是指日可待的
And when you graduate,
到时候等你毕业的时候
you will be able to be recommended as the best.
还能够推优
What a bright future!
未来可期呀
OK.
嗯
And then?
然后呢
Find a good job.
找份好工作
Just like you?
就跟你一样是吧
As long as you work hard,
只要你努力
you can achieve it.
是能够达得到的
So, what is a good job?
哎呀 什么是好工作呀
Mr. Sa, being a teacher in this school
撒老师你现在留校
at least
最起码也得是
must be a graduate student, right?
研究生毕业吧
After great efforts, you made it.
好不容易混到这个留校
And then you encounter such a mess
就遇到二队
like team two.
这么个烂摊子
However, you can't reject it.
还没法撂
You still rely on it for promotion and salary increase.
还靠它升职加薪呢
Then you'll work harder.
然后好不容易
After three to five years,
再混个三五年
maybe you'll become the Secretary of the Youth League Committee.
混成团委书记
And then you will be 30 years old at that time.
那会儿也得三十岁了吧
Is this what you called "a bright future"?
这就是你说的未来可期
Wait, wait.
等 等
Why are you looking at me like that?
你 你干嘛这么看着我
Maybe my words were
我可能刚刚话
a little bit harsh.
说得有点重
Ma Nan,
马楠同学
let me tell you a story.
我给你讲一个故事吧
Go ahead.
你讲
On July 3,
一五一八年
1518,
七月三日
in a medical family
在今天的湖北省
in Qichun County,
蕲春县
Hubei Province,
一个医药世家中
a baby made his first cry of life.
一个婴儿呱呱坠地
His parents named him
他的父母给他取名叫做
Li Shizhen.
李时珍
But, wait a minute.
不 等等等等
Why are you telling me this?
你 你跟我说这些干嘛
Li Shizhen is a
这个李时珍啊
medical scientist,
医学家
and a pharmaceutist.
药学家
He created a masterpiece
他创作了192万字的
of 1.92 million words.
巨著
It's Compendium of Materia Medica.
《本草纲目》
He also wrote "An Examination of the Eight Extra Meridians",
还著有《奇经八脉考》
and "A Study of the Pulse", etc.
《濒湖脉学》等
But I've learned
不是 这些东西
all these things from my high school textbooks.
我高中课本里都学
What can we learn
从他的故事里
from his story?
我们学到了什么呢
He is a person
他是一位
who will not be intimidated by difficulties
不会被困难所吓倒
and will not be confused by success.
不会被成功所迷惑的人
He worked tirelessly
他不屈不挠地
towards his great goal.
迈向了自己的伟大目标
So
从而
he would not act rashly.
不会轻举妄动
He moved forward steadily
稳步向前
and never retreated.
而从不后退
He is a person
他是一位到达了
who has reached a great level
伟大境界
but still maintains
而仍然保持着
his excellent characters.
自己优秀品格
How rare such a person is!
的罕见的人
Though being outstanding
而这样一位出类拔萃
and virtuous,
道德高尚的人
he's modest at the same time,
却又是那么的谦虚
so that
以至于
after more than 500 years later,
以至于五百多年
in modern world,
后的今天
his Compendium of Materia Medica
他的《本草纲目》
is still of great significance.
仍具有重要意义
But, but...
不 不是
what are you trying to say?
你到底想说什么
Ma Nan,
马楠同学
Don't you think
你不觉得这种
such glorious deeds are stimulating?
光辉事迹很燃吗
Haven't you been touched
你没有被感染到
and inspired?
热血沸腾吗
No.
没有
Mr. Sa, I have something else to do.
小撒老师 我还有点事
I'll go now.
我先走了
I'm not finished.
我 我没说完呢
Ma Nan,
马楠同学
Would you like to hear the story of
华盛顿跟斧头的故事
Washington and the axe?
你要不要听一下
Didn't it inspire him?
这都没有燃到他吗
It seems that I have to keep trying.
我还得继续努力呀
Ma Nan,
马楠同学
I will save you.
我一定会拯救你的
Oh, dear!
哎哟
Why are you again?
怎么又是你啊
Yes.
对
It's me.
是我
Ma Nan
马楠同学
Have you made your decision
加入辩论队的事情
about joining us?
考虑得怎么样了
No.
不加
What's your purpose, anyway?
你到底想干什么
Let me tell you a story.
我来给你讲个故事吧
I won't listen.
我不听
I want to hear nothing about celebrity stories.
我不听什么名人事迹
It's not a story of a celebrity.
不是名人事迹
What's that?
那是什么
Do you know salmon?
你知道鲑鱼吗
Salmon?
鲑鱼
Salmon is also called oncorhynchus keta.
又叫大马哈鱼
It is
这是一种
an incredible fish.
不可思议的鱼类
They live in
它们生活在
freshwater rivers and lakes,
淡水的江河湖泊当中
but spend
却在大海当中
most of their adult time
度过了它大部分的
in the sea.
成年时光
Every time it comes to spawning,
每到产卵期
they will migrate thousands of miles
它就会不惜千里
to their hometowns
洄游到它的故乡
to produce their offspring,
繁衍下一代
and die
而产卵结束之后
after spawning.
它们就会力尽而死
And the inheritance of life
而生命的传承
lies in the cycle of
就在这洄游的
migration,
周而复始当中
generation
一代
after generation.
又一代
But
不是
what does this have to do with
这跟我加不加入辩论队
whether I join the debate team or not?
有什么关系啊
Who
是谁
guides them
在冥冥之中
in the unseen world?
指引着它们
Despite the encirclement and interception
尽管路途当中有人类
of big brown bears,
大棕熊
bald eagles, and humans,
白头鹰的围追堵截
they still go forward bravely
它们依然
through thousands of difficulties
历尽千难万险
and dangers.
勇往直前
Don't you feel
这生命的律动
the rhythm of life's beating?
你没有觉得很燃吗
Haven't you been touched
你没有被
and inspired?
感染到热血沸腾吗
No, not at all.
没 没有
Mr. Sa, I still have something else to do.
小撒老师 我还有事
I need to go.
我先走了
But I haven't finished yet.
可是我还没讲完呢
Ma Nan
马楠
Don't you want to
你不想听一下
hear the story of the Tibetan antelope
非洲大草原上
on the African savannah?
瞪羚羊的故事吗
Ma Nan
马楠
Why are you again?
怎么又是你啊
Ma Nan,
马楠同学
About joining our debate team...
加入辩论队的事情
I refuse, I refuse.
我拒绝 我拒绝
So,
那
let me tell you a story.
我给你讲个故事吧
Oh, I don't want to listen to
哎呀 我不要听
the story of celebrity deeds,
什么名人事迹
nor animal world.
动物世界
I don't want to listen to that.
我不要听啊
It's not a celebrity story,
不是名人事迹
nor is it the animal world.
也不是动物世界
So, what's that?
那是什么故事啊
There is a galaxy
在距离地球
2.54 million
两百五十四万
light years
光年的地方
away from the earth.
有一个星系
Zip it.
闭嘴
OK.
那
I'll change another one.
换一个
Ma Nan
马楠同学
When did you come?
你 你什么时候来的
Since you started
从你开始玩
playing the first round.
第一盘的时候
Then why are you as quiet as a mouse?
那你怎么不吭一声呢
You scared me to death!
吓死我了
Because I saw you playing very attentively.
因为我看你玩得很专注
Well, of course,
当然呐
I was also fascinated by it.
我自己也看得入了迷
So,
所以呢
I didn't want to interrupt you.
我就没有忍心叫你
Wait a minute, wait a minute.
等会儿 等会儿
No, don't come over.
别 别过来
Stop it!
别说了
Ma Nan
马楠同学
Have you made your decision
加入辩论队的事情
about joining team two?
你考虑得怎么样
Stop it.
你别说了
I won't join you.
我是不可能答应的
All right.
好吧
Then let me tell you a story.
那我给你讲个故事吧
No, no, no.
别 别 别
I want to hear nothing
什么名人事迹
about celebrities
动物世界
nor animal world.
我都不想听
In fact, I still have many other
其实我还是有很多
exhilarating stories.
其他很燃的故事的
Ma Nan
马楠同学
Ma Nan, let your youth sparkling with brightness.
马楠 让青春燃烧吧
Man can't live twice.
人无再少年呐
Ma Nan
马楠
Yes.
嗯
What are you packing for?
你收拾东西干嘛
My dad texted me
我爸发短信让我
to go home.
回去一趟
Okay.
哦
Sa said...
那个小撒说要
Don't mention
千万不要跟我
the word "Sa" to me.
提小撒这两个字
Ma Nan
马楠同学
Ma Nan...
马楠同
Where is he?
人呢
He has gone.
跑了
My son,
儿子
Why do you suddenly
怎么突然
run back home in such a hurry?
这么急着跑回家了呀
Nothing, I just want to have a look.
没事 就回来看看
Now that you're back,
既然回来了
let's handle some affairs
正好 明天一早呢
early tomorrow morning.
我们一起办点事
Handle affairs?
办事
What affairs?
办什么事
You don't have to know.
不用问了
Anyway, you'll know it tomorrow.
明天你就知道了
Uh
这
What's going on?
什么情况这是
Buying a house.
买房呀
Buying a house?
买房
Ah?
啊
But...
不是
What's this for?
住得好好的买什么房呀
If you don't buy a house, how will you marry a wife?
不买房拿什么娶媳妇啊
But, but...
不是 不是
That's not what your dad meant.
你爸不是这意思
We are trying to say
我们是说呀
if you have a girlfriend
万一你谈女朋友了
and want to marry her,
要结婚
at that time
那到那时候
the house prices
这房价
will never be the same.
涨得可不是这个数了
Yeah.
是啊
As soon as you went to college,
你一上大学
your mother and I began planning
我和你妈就开始规划
to buy a house.
买房子的事
And now
正好现在
the money is almost ready,
钱存得差不多了
and you are about to graduate,
你也快毕业了
How nice!
多好啊
Hey.
哎
Nan
那个 楠楠啊
That's not what we meant.
我跟你爸不是这意思
We're not forcing you
没有说非得逼着
to graduate right away.
你马上毕业
I mean,
我是说呀
you've grown up.
你看你也这么大了
You advocate freedom.
崇尚自由
So, what kind of lifestyle
你想选择你将来
you want to choose in the future
什么样的生活方式呢
is your freedom.
那是你的自由
Your father and I have no right to interfere.
我跟你爸无权干涉
Yeah, yeah.
对对对
But it's also our freedom
但是我跟你爸替你着想
to take care of you,
那也是我们的自由呀
and you have no right to interfere.
你也无权干涉
Yes.
嗯
Look this.
过来看看
Look this house
快来看这房子
with two rooms and two halls.
两室两厅
How big this hall is!
你看这厅多大
And look at the balcony.
还有你看这阳台
If we seal it up,
如果把它封起来
we can make a small study.
还能做个小书房呢
Are you Ma Nan?
你就是马楠吧
Please show me your ID card.
麻烦身份证给我看一下
Why?
为什么要我身份证
Wait a moment.
稍等
No problem.
没问题
Here,
来
please sign your name.
你请签个字吧
Go ahead.
签
My son,
来 儿子
eat more.
多吃点菜啊
You must be sick of
学校菜
your school's dishes.
肯定都吃腻了
By the way,
对了
This month's living expenses
这个月生活费呀
have been transferred to you.
我给你转过去了
Thank you.
谢谢爸
Never mind.
还学会客气了
Wait,
等等 先别吃
we should celebrate first.
我们应该先庆祝一下
Our son, Nan,
我们家小楠
have a house now.
也是有房一族了呀
OK.
嗯
Shouldn't we? Yes, it's worth a celebration.
是不是  是得庆祝一下
Come on, cheers!
来 干杯
Cheers!
干杯
Don't drink to the last drop.
别喝完啊
Can you drink less?
你不能喝少喝点
It's bad for your health.
对身体不好
Ah
哎
Ma
老马
That...
那
Should we change the water in the fishbowl?
鱼缸的水是不该换了
You see, the fish are wilting.
你看那鱼都蔫巴了
Yes.
嗯
Do it when you're free.
你抽空换换啊
I'll do it tomorrow.
明天我换
Okay.
嗯
We can't help but give in to the age.
这不服老是不行的
Look at my face,
你看这脸
and my hair
还有这上面
is all white.
全都白了
Yeah.
是呀
My eyesight is growing dim with age.
我这眼都花了
I can't see things clearly.
我看都看不清楚
Exactly.
你呀 花得厉害
Here, the hair here is still white.
这儿 看 这儿全是白的
Haven't I told you to go to the barbershop to dye it?
不是让你去理发店染吗
You insist on dyeing it at home.
你非得在家染
How inconvenient!
这不麻烦吗
There's no big difference.
理发店也就那么回事
What are we wasting that money for?
浪费那钱干啥
Here.
这儿
Okay, okay.
好好好
You missed here.
都没染上
Be patient.
你别着急呀
Nan
儿子
Is the water in the fishbowl...
鱼缸的水是
Gone?
走了
There is a group of people
世界上就是
like us in the world.
有一群我们这样的人
We really don't know
我们真的不知道
what our dreams are.
自己的梦想到底是什么
And the evaluation
而对方立场下
from the other side's position
的这种评价
labelled us with a concept
就是给我们贴上了一种
called mediocrity.
叫做平庸的
Of course, everyone has the freedom
每个人当然都有选择
to choose his own way of life,
自己生活方式的自由
but
但
that should be on the premise of
那应该是在不去剥夺
not depriving others
别人选择权利
of their right to choose.
的前提下的
Hello, Nan Bei.
喂 南北
Where were you last night?
你昨晚去哪儿了
I telephoned, and you didn't answer.
电话也不接
I came back home.
我回了趟家
Do me a favor, please.
你帮我个忙呗
What?
说
In my drawer,
你去我那个抽屉里
the third drawer,
第三个抽屉
there's a student card.
找一下我学生证
Check out my student card number,
看下我学生证号
and help me sign up for the CET-4.
帮我报个四级
No problem.
没有问题
And
还有
is there still a vacancy in your team?
你们队还缺人吗
Come on!
来吧
Let me lead you to beat team one.
让我带领你们干翻一队
Package 7301,
七三零一号快递
is this yours?
是你们的吗
No?
不是吧
Excuse me.
打扰了
I'm here to ask you,
我来问问你
have I signed up for that exam?
我那个名报好了吗
Yes.
报好了
And?
然后呢
And
然后
I've made up my mind.
我决定了
I'll be your fourth debater.
我来当你们的四辩
Next is the most exciting
下面就是大家最期待的
"free debate" part
紧张刺激的
that you are looking forward to.
自由辩论环节
Now, let's invite
接下来让我们有请
debaters from both sides.
双方辩手
Thank you, Mr. Chairman.
谢谢主席
Let me confirm our consensus
确认一下共识
on "comfort zone".
所谓舒适圈
It is an environment that allows
就是一个能够让
young people to be more comfortable
年轻人比较自在
and give full play to their value,
且能发挥价值的环境
right?
对不对
What is "more comfortable"?
什么叫比较自在
More comfortable than what?
跟谁比较
What value to play?
发挥什么价值
And give full play to whose value?
谁的价值
Um.
嗯
Being more comfortable means that
比较自在就是说
it is more comfortable
相对于不自在
than being uncomfortable.
它是自在的
In terms of the value,
价值呢
It means that the environment
就是说这个环境
can help him realize his self-value.
能帮他实现自我价值
The comfort zone of boomerang kids
啃老族的舒适圈
is relying on parents.
就是在家吃父母
So, what value do they create?
请问他创造什么价值
His value is
他的价值就是
to accompany his parents.
给予父母陪伴啊
Keeping a dog
你养条狗
can also keep you company.
也能陪伴你呀
Is this the value
请问这是它
it creates?
创造的价值吗
No, this is its born value.
这是它自带的价值呀
Therefore, your explanation
所以对方辩友
of realizing value
对创造价值的定义
is somewhat farfetched.
完全就是牵强附会
Your view is to jump out of the comfort zone,
您方观点是跳出舒适圈
but if the comfort zone is very comfortable,
可是既然舒适圈很舒适
why should we jump out?
我为什么要跳出去呢
Lying down is comfortable,
躺着很舒服
why should I sit up?
为什么我要坐起来呢
This chair is very comfortable,
这个椅子坐着很舒服
then why should I stand up?
为什么我要站起来呢
Because only when I stand up and speak,
因为只有我站起来发言
can I get applause
才可以获得
from the audience. Right?
观众们的掌声不是吗
Just now our second debater
刚才我方二辩
also stood up,
也站起来了
and then he stuttered.
然后卡壳了
Therefore, standing up bravely
所以勇敢地站起来
may gain applause
可能收获掌声
or embarrassment,
也可能收获尴尬
but sitting there will never be embarrassed.
但坐着一定不会尴尬
It would be deeply embarrassing
那如果你们对面
when none of you
四个都不站
stood up.
那是真尴尬
My fellow debaters, let's get straight to the point.
对方辩友不妨直接点
Are you suffering
跳出舒适圈
when you jump out of your comfort zone?
是不是找罪受
Is discomfort equal to suffering?
不舒适就等于受罪吗
Isn't it?
难道不是吗
I'm exhausted when I go to the gym.
我去健身这个过程很累
It must be uncomfortable.
肯定是不舒适的
But when I got sweaty,
但是我出了一身汗
it is great fun for me.
我很爽啊
Is it a suffering?
这算不算找罪受呢
I feel comfortable when working out.
健身我觉得很舒适
This is comfortable to you.
您方这也舒适
That is comfortable to you.
那也舒适
All in all,
总的来说
You are comfortable to everything
只要有利于
as long as it is conducive to your team.
您方的都舒适
We are
您这样
very uncomfortable with this.
让我方很不舒适啊
They are addictive to
他们这是
playing petty tricks.
抖机灵抖上瘾了
We're not the first one to do this.
是对方先抖的
They can only blame themselves.
谁让他们兜不住
Well.
嗯
Let's set aside the snarky answers,
机灵抖完了
and turn to something practical.
咱们来看点实际的
There are many century-old stores in Japan.
日本有很多百年老店
They developed deeply
他们在自己的舒适圈
within their comfort zone.
内不断深耕
Although they didn't jump out of the zone,
虽然没有出圈
they still adapt well to the world.
但依然适应得不错
Right?
对吗
What's the specific number of these stores?
很多是多少
Hundreds or thousands?
几百家还是几千家
What is their proportion
他们在日本历史中
in Japanese history?
商家占的比例
One thousandth
是千分之一
or one ten-thousandth?
还是万分之一
So why don't you mention
那其他大多数
most of the them?
为什么对面不提呢
Regardless of data,
不论数据
this example at least shows
但这个例子至少说明
that even if I don't jump out of the comfort zone,
哪怕我不跳出舒适圈
as long as I focus on my own business,
只要我专注地做好自己
I won't be eliminated.
人就不会被淘汰
Nokia, a former mobile phone giant,
曾经的手机巨头诺基亚
has focused on implementing
专注地贯彻
"technology based on shell changing"
科技以换壳为本
to make the function machine.
来做功能机
Please tell me,
请问他现在的
what is its current
手机市场份额
mobile phone market share?
又是多少呢
Let's push the time earlier.
我们把时间拉长来看
GINZA Sushiko in Tokyo
东京银座寿司幸本店
has been making sushi for 120 years.
做了一百二十年寿司
Isn't it doing well
在它的舒适圈内
in its comfort zone?
不是做得很好吗
Yamaha acting willfully.
为所欲为雅马哈
Nintendo changing its profession.
改行游戏任天堂
Michelin running irrelevant business relentlessly.
不务正业米其林
Which of these similar century old stores
这些同样的百年老店
is not world-famous
哪个不是
after jumping out of
跳出舒适圈之后
their comfort zone?
而世界闻名的
However, I know nothing about
倒是您说的那家寿司店
the sushi restaurant you just mentioned.
我是真没听说
Yamaha didn't give up on
雅马哈造船的同时
the practice of repairing pianos while building ships.
也没有放弃修琴的本行
Michelin didn't delay making tires
米其林写美食指南
when it wrote food guides.
也没有耽误造轮胎
They didn't jump out of the comfort circle,
他们不是跳出了舒适圈
but constantly expanded the boundary
而是不断地拓开边界
of their comfort zone.
扩大自己的舒适圈
Isn't this
这难道不是
a better choice?
更好的选择吗
The expansion of Michelin and Yamaha
米其林和雅马哈的拓展
is based on their century old foundation,
基于他们的百年基业
but most of the young people
而我们今天所
we are talking about today
讨论的年轻人呢
only have
我们有的只是
some years of hard study.
十年寒窗而已
Our comfort zone
我们的舒适圈
is just a foothold under our feet.
不过是脚下的立锥之地
My fellow debaters,
对方辩友
how nostalgic are you
到底是有多恋旧
that you won't jump out of your comfort zone?
就是不肯跳出去呢
But, my fellow debaters,
可是 对方辩友
don't I have the right
难道我没有选择
to stay in my comfort zone?
留在舒适圈里的权利吗
Do all young people
难道年轻人就一定要
have to be constrained by the pep talk
被奋斗拼搏
like "never give up"?
这样的鸡汤绑架吗
Can't I stay in my comfort zone
我不能待在
and enjoy a tranquil and comfortable life?
舒适圈里岁月静好
Isn't that feasible?
这样不行吗
Of course, you can, but...
当然可以 但
We are hopeful!
有戏 有戏 有戏 有戏
Thanks to the fourth debater from Team NEG's
感谢反方四辩的
wonderful speech.
精彩陈词
Now, let's move on to
下面就是本场比赛
the final summary of the Team AFF.
最后的正方总结陈词
Let's welcome the fourth debater from Team AFF.
接下来有请正方四辩
Thank you.
谢谢
You just asked us
对面刚才问
if we have the right
我们到底有没有
not to jump out of the comfort zone.
不跳出舒适圈的权利
Of course, we do.
当然有
In the face of life and death,
面对生死
we have the right
我们有选择
to choose to live.
求生不死的权利
In the face of interests,
面对利害
we have the right
我们有选择
to pursue advantages.
趋利避害的权利
However, why do people with lofty ideals in ancient and modern times
但为何古今多仁人志士
are concerned about the society all the time?
处处传慷慨悲歌呢
Because in addition to our rights,
因为除了权利之外
we also have responsibilities,
我们还有责任
duties,
担当
and future.
和未来
What is a comfort zone
对于年轻人而言
for young people?
什么是舒适圈呢
Today, you've used
对面今天用了
a lot of words and phrases
大量的遣词造句
to try to
来试图
delineate the scope of the comfort zone.
圈定舒适圈的范围
I don't this is necessary.
我认为大可不必
What is exactly a comfortable zone?
什么是舒适圈
A job
一份做起来
that is not too bad.
还不错的工作
A place
一处住起来
that is not too awful.
还不错的住处
A living environment
一个生活着起来
that is not too terrible.
还不错的环境
Maybe you can define the comfort zone
也许你可以把舒适圈
as "not bad",
定义为还不错
but when you want to change your major
但当你要转专业
and want to change your job,
想要换工作的时候
you will be extremely frustrated.
我们会万般纠结
Because you already
因为我们已经有了这个
have your corner that is not too bad.
还不错的一亩三分地
Would it be better to
转了专业
change a major or a job?
换了工作会更好吗
I don't know.
不知道
But jumping out of this zone
但是跳出
makes better possible.
会让更好成为一种可能
At this time,
这个时候
the comfort zone that is not too bad
还不错的舒适圈
will become
反而会变成
a mental shackle that will limit you.
限制我们的紧箍咒
So, we believe that
我方认为
the nature of the comfort zone
舒适圈的本质
is by no means "not too bad".
绝不是还不错
It is a habit,
它是一种行为习惯
a life inertia.
一种生活惯性
And inertia
而惯性
is a
是一种
huge
巨大
and fearful power.
而可怕的力量
The more comfortable you are
当你在你的舒适圈里
in your comfort zone,
越得心应手的时候
the more you are used to
你就越习惯于
controlling everything there.
控制这里的一切
Once you get used to it,
一旦你习以为常
who on earth
到底是谁
controls who?
控制了谁呢
Some people questioned that
有同学代点到
isn't it cool to truant?
逃课它不香吗
Isn't it cool to be
总是有新生
the top dog among freshmen
向你打听
who always ask you for information?
学校内幕他不帅吗
You don't need to face the cruelty of society,
不用面对社会的残酷
but you don't have the ability to make money to support the family.
没有赚钱能力养家
But so what?
又如何呢
However, once you indulge yourself
一旦你沉醉在
in that small world,
这一方天地中时
is the school
学校
your comfort zone
到底是你的舒适圈
or a nursing home?
还是养老院呢
When we turn habits into pursuits,
当我们把习惯变成追求
when we indulge ourselves
当我们沉醉于
in the arcadia,
桃花源中无论魏晋
and when we get used to
当我们习惯了
all our habits,
我们一切的习惯的时候
even if one day you realize
即使有一天
that your comfort zone
你发现你的舒适圈
is a "The Truman Show",
是楚门的世界
you've already got used to
可你却早已习惯于
the narrow sky in the cave,
洞中方一日
and how can you face
又怎能面对
the world's unmeasured vastness.
世上已千年
Thank you.
谢谢
The result of this game
本场比赛的结果
is now in my hands.
现在已经在我手上了
I declare that
接下来我宣布
the winner of this debate
本场辩论赛的获胜方是
is the Team AFF.
正方
The debate team from DUFE.
东州财经大学辩论队
Hello, dad.
喂 爸
Hi.
哎
Nan
小楠啊
What's your
你那个银行账号
bank account number?
是多少啊
It's Okay.
没事
I'll go back home
这周末我再回去一趟
and have dinner with you this weekend.
跟家里人吃个饭
I haven't been back for a long time.
好久没回去了
Alright.
啊 行
So, you don't have to remit money to me.
钱不用打
By the way, I'm working part-time now.
我现在兼职呢
I have money.
不用打钱啊
But
不是
you have to deposit
你现在银行账号里啊
6,000 yuan a month
每个月要固定
in your bank account.
有六千块钱
You have to pay the mortgage
每个月月底呢
at the end of each month.
要还房贷
Cheer up!
你可要加油啊
Our topic today
我们今天的议题
is to retrospect our last game.
就是来复盘上一场比赛
Although we
我们虽然在比赛当中
won the game,
获得了胜利
we
但是
still exposed
却暴露出了
a lot of problems.
很多问题
So, today we'll look for problems.
今天我们就来找问题
Who says first?
谁先说
Actually,
大家这次
everyone did very well this time.
其实表现得都挺好的
Dango
团子
Thank you, Hao.
谢谢小好姐
Does anyone want to summarize?
有没有谁想总结一下呀
Nan Bei, you act shamelessly.
南北 你耍赖
I'll buy you fried chicken after the retrospection.
复完盘我请客吃炸鸡
I, I, I, I think
我我我 我觉得呀
the biggest hero of this competition
这场比赛最大的功臣
should be Mu Xiaoyu student.
应该是牧小鱼同学
She is absolutely the best.
她呀 绝对的奶妈
Oho,
哎哟
you have also shown admirable behavior.
你也不错嘛
However, our great hero
不过呀 咱们的大功臣
is still our first debater,
还是我们的一辩
sister Tao Hao.
陶好姐
Your speech
你的发言稿
paved the way for our victory.
那是使我们旗开得胜
Don't say that.
没有 没有
It's mainly because
主要是还有
our fourth debater,
我们的灵魂四辩
comrade Ma Nan.
马楠同志
Me?
还有我事呢
How about me?
那我呢
Dango
团子
As the leader
你作为我们的
of the logistics team
后勤组组长
and the
和我们的
cheering team,
后啦啦队队长呢
Your performance
你的发挥
is perfect!
那简直是堪称完美
You shocked the cheerleaders
你让对面的啦啦队
from the opposite team into silence.
那都不敢吱声了
Really?
真的
Enough.
停
Stop it.
住手
Stop
停止
this round of business flattery.
这一轮的商业互捧
Our topic today
我们今天的议题
is to find problems.
主题就是找问题
How can there be so many problems?
哪儿那么多问题呀
Coach Sa
撒教练
Can we stop
咱能不能
being so picky?
别那么吹毛求疵啊
Treat you guys to hot pot this evening.
晚上吃火锅
I think there are no big problems,
我觉得大问题没有
but there still lies some small problems.
小问题还是有的
Someone among us
咱们中间啊
got trapped
被绕进去
but got away in time, luckily.
但是及时脱开了
Yes.
嗯
Who are you blaming here?
你在这儿指桑骂谁呢你
Who was trapped
中间到底是因为谁
by the other party's
被对方的那个逻辑
logic setting,
绕进去了
Nan Bei?
南北同学
Me, it's me.
我 是我 是我
It's mainly my problem.
主要还是我的问题
My argument is not perfect enough.
我的立论还不够完善
Hao.
小好姐
It has nothing to do with you.
这事跟你没关系
It's Ma.
主要是那个姓马的
What the hell
他的辩论
is his speech?
什么玩意
No ,no, no.
不是 不是
The main reason is that
主要是我的框架
my framework is not perfect enough,
不够完整
which makes the Team NEG take some advantages.
让对方钻了漏洞
OK, I forgive you.
行 我原谅你了
Well,
我说
You've been debating for so many years.
你们打了这么多年比赛
Is this your ideological level?
就这水平啊
How can you
一个个推得
shirk your responsibilities like this?
比我兜还干净
All right.
好了
Let me do the summary.
还是靠我吧
Now,
下面呢
I will
就由我
make the retrospection to you.
来给大家复盘一下
The biggest problem of team two
二队最大的问题
is that the second debater is too weak.
就是二辩太弱
Why are you everywhere?
怎么哪儿都有你呀
The biggest problem with your team
你们队伍最大的问题
is that problems are everywhere.
就是全是问题
Oh, wait.
哎哟喂
Calm down, calm down.
冷静 冷静
We are all school teams
我们现在都是校队
and we should help each other.
互帮互助
We've established rules
定过规矩吧
on the usage of this classroom.
这个教室
This classroom is for us after eight o'clock.
八点之后是我们用
Is it time up? Is it time up?
到点了吗 到点了吗
Not yet...
没到点
You.
你们
Enough.
好了
Students,
同学们
We're all school teams.
都是学校的队伍
There's no need to
没有必要一见面
contrast sharply as soon as we meet.
就这么剑拔弩张的吧
There is always a way
总还是有办法
to get what we need.
可以各取所需的
Take what we need. That's right.
各取所需没错
So, now
所以现在
we need to use this classroom.
我们需要用这间教室了
Yin Nan
殷楠
Calm down.
冷静
Let me handle this.
交给我
There!
怎么样
Isn't the air pure and fresh here?
空气清新吧
The air quality in the classroom is bad.
教室里面空气不流通
And it will affect our thinking.
影响思路
Well.
好了
God bless the person with a strong will.
天将降大任嘛
Think positively.
想开点
I'll go on retrospecting.
我接着复盘啊
Each of you
上一场比赛
had some problems
你们每一个人
in the last game.
都有一定的问题
No one can run away from this.
谁也跑不掉
To sum up, there are four points.
总结起来就是四点
Stiff, stubborn, showy, and soft.
僵 死 秀 佛
Tao Hao, you are too stiff.
陶好你是僵
Tao Hao, your argument is
陶好你的一辩位
very excellent.
非常优秀
You have done a very good job
立论大旗
in both argument setting
定义辨析
and definition differentiating.
做得都非常好
When related problems arose,
但有这些问题
you would always appear
出现的时候
at once.
你都会第一时间出现
But
但是
when other problems came out,
当无关于此的时候
I couldn't see you at all.
却完全看不见你
Your label of the first debater
你的一辩标签
is so obvious
太过于明显
that your opponent can guess clearly
以至于你什么时候出现
when you appear
什么时候不出现
and when you don't appear.
让对手猜得一清二楚
In the end,
到最后
you won't have
会不给你
any room to show yourself.
任何的发挥空间
You're too stiff.
太僵了
Do you understand?
明白吗
"Stubborn" is for Nan Bei.
死是南北
Ah?
啊
Nan, your responsibility is to defend,
南北你二辩位主守
and you've done it well, too.
守得也很好
But I didn't ask you to hide yourself all the time
但是没让你死守城池
and not to attack their palace.
龟缩不出吧
Attack it when needed.
该进攻时则进攻
Okay?
对不对
I won't go into the palace.
我不进宫
Go in it if you want to,
要进你进吧
and serve imperial concubine.
你伺候娘娘去吧
I won't do it.
我不伺候
Use all your jokes
把你这些俏皮话
on attacking.
都用在进攻上
Compared with the "stubborn" of Nan Bei,
相比于南北的死
you're too showy, Yu.
小鱼你就是太秀了
You mean, outstanding?
优秀的秀吗
No.
不是
Let's look at the game records.
大家看一下比赛记录
You alone took 25
全场三十三次进攻
of all 33 attacks.
你自己占了二十五次
As long as there was an opportunity to attack,
只要是有进攻机会
you would seize it with all your efforts.
就玩命地抓
But you forgot to consider
但是完全不管这次进攻
whether your attack
能不能作用于
can help with our main logic or not.
我们的主逻辑
So,
所以呢
of your 25 attacks,
在你的二十五次进攻中
only ten
只有十次
made the argument stronger.
推动了立论
The rest
剩下的呢
are all snarky answers.
都是在抖包袱
Some people knew it was a debate,
知道的这是辩论
while others
不知道的
would think you were performing a comic dialogue.
以为你说相声呢
Don't be so showy next time.
以后不许这么秀啊
Oh.
哦
Dango
团子
You're good!
你很好
At last, I'll comment on Ma Nan.
最后我们来说一下马楠
Ma Nan's conclusion
马楠的结辩
is excellent.
很优秀
Very excellent.
可以说是非常优秀
But
但是
at least say something
在你结辩之外
apart from your conclusion.
你好歹说句话吧
Isn't it a bit wasteful
以你的能力
not to make up for deficiencies
不查缺补漏
with your ability?
是不是有点太浪费了
You're too soft.
太佛了
No bad, Sa.
可以呀 小撒
Coach Sa.
撒教练
Coach Sa, how can you hide your light under a bushel?
撒教练深藏不露啊
Alright,
好了 以上
these are all your problems.
就是你们的所有问题
The next game
下一场比赛
is very important for us.
对咱们来讲非常重要
And it's getting closer.
而且时间越来越近了
Let's have a meeting tomorrow morning
明天咱们早上开一个会
to formulate tactics.
制定一下战术
That's all for today
今天就到这里
for I have to talk to the old coach.
我还要跟老教练
Hey, wait a minute.
哎 等会儿
What about hot pot and fried chicken?
火锅炸鸡呢
The meeting ended!
散会
Coach, you took your cell phone upside down.
教练 你手机拿反了
Do you still cough?
你不咳嗽了吧
You took your cell phone upside down.
你手机拿反了
Then I'll go first.
那我也先走了
Hao
小好姐
Don't go
你这几天胃不舒服
if your stomach doesn't feel well.
你就别去了嘛
It's much better.
已经好多了
And I have an appointment with my boyfriend.
而且我约了男朋友
You can see him some other day.
男朋友嘛 就改天呗
We have an appointment,
我们约好了
and he's already waiting for me.
而且他已经在等我了
Yu, you don't understand.
小鱼 这你就不懂了
The power of love
爱情的力量
can cure everything.
是可以治愈一切的
I must go.
那我先走了
Bye.
拜拜
She looks
小好姐最近看起来
very tired recently.
好像很累的样子
I'm worried about her health.
真怕她身体被累垮
There are many things to cope with
她学生会的事情
in the student union.
本来就很多了
And recently, she started her internship in a company.
最近又开始在公司实习
Yeah, I've heard about it.
是啊 听说了
Employees in the department
她实习的那个部门
where she interned are almost retiring.
其他员工都快退休了
Because
因为她把
she did everything.
所有事都干完了
I'm afraid she can't hold on.
真怕她坚持不住啊
What are you doing here?
你来干嘛
I'm just hanging around.
我就来随便逛逛啊
Since you've done the usage of this classroom,
你们都用完教室了
I should be able to come in.
我应该可以进来吧
I told you
我都跟你说了
not to bring me desserts.
不要给我带这种甜食
Oh.
哦
This is
这个是
for me.
我给我自己准备的
Oh.
哦
Please go on.
那你继续
Golden color.
那黄金的颜色
Crisp sound.
酥脆的声响
Thick milky flavor.
浓浓的奶香
How creamy and sweet!
香滑 甜蜜
Senior
学长
Ah?
嗯
Are you all right?
你没事吧
I saw you've been in a daze.
我看你刚刚一直在发呆
Oh.
哦
I'm all right.
我没事
Would you like one?
你是想吃一个吗
Can I?
我可以吗
Of course.
当然了
Excuse me.
不好意思
What shall we have for lunch?
吃什么
Whatever you decide.
都行吧
Hand-pulled noodles?
拉面
What about hot pot?
火锅吧
Oh, you have an upset stomach.
哦对 你胃不舒服
Let's have hand-pulled noodles.
那咱们吃拉面吧
As soon as you say hot pot,
你一说吃火锅
I suddenly want to eat it, too.
我突然想吃火锅了
Let's have hot pot.
就火锅吧
Can you do that?
你行不行啊
You don't have to accommodate yourself to me every time.
你不用每次都迁就我
I didn't.
我没有迁就你
I really want to eat it.
我是真的想吃
It just comes into my head suddenly.
我就是随口一说
We can go to a tea restaurant.
要不咱们茶餐厅吧
Just take it as going there in company of me.
你就当陪我吃吧
Are you sure?
你确定
Don't worry, I'm fine.
放心吧 我没事
Why does Hao have stomachache again?
小好姐怎么又胃疼了
Nan Bei, shall we deliver the medicine
咱俩要不先把药
to her home now?
送过去吧 南北
She is out on a date,
人都出去约会了
how can she come back so fast?
哪儿能回来那么快啊
Her boyfriend's a little bit tactless.
这小好姐男朋友真是的
Hao's not feeling well.
身体本来就不舒服
Why not rest in the dormitory
不在寝室好好躺着
but go on a date?
出去约什么会
Don't you know Hao?
小好姐你还不了解
She always accommodates others
只有她迁就别人的份
with no exception.
别人哪能迁就她呀
If others accommodate her once,
迁就一次
she will suffer for several days.
她就难受好几天
What do you mean "others"?
什么叫别人
Aren't they lovers?
那不是男女朋友吗
It's not a big deal for a man
男朋友 男朋友
to yield to his girlfriend.
迁就一下女朋友怎么了
Hey.
哎
There is a milk tea shop there.
那儿有个奶茶店
Do you want to have a drink or not?
喝不喝
I am a little full.
我刚才吃得也有点饱
It's my treat.
我请客
I'll have a venti.
超大杯
38 yuan per cup.
三十八一杯
So expensive. But why there are still so many people lining up?
这么贵这么多人排队
We have a promotion today.
我们今天搞促销
Lovers buy one can get extra one for free.
情侣买一送一
Baby, it's nice to have you.
宝宝有你真好
Thank you.
感恩有你
Can we separate?
能放开了吗
Don't worry.
别急呀
We're not out of their sight yet.
还没有脱离视野范围内
What taste is this?
不 什么味的
What's your taste?
你的什么味
I don't know. Maybe pineapple.
我不知道 我这凤梨的
Let me have a taste.
我尝尝
Did we take the wrong one?
咱俩是不是拿错了
Isn't it all clearly written here?
这不写着呢吗
Really?
写着呢吗
Can we separate now?
能不能放开
Maybe.
差不多
Get away from me.
滚开
Where's my dinner card?
你说我这饭卡去哪了
You're always forgetful.
天天丢三落四的
Stop lecturing me, please.
别说我啦
I tell you
这两人特别逗
they are very funny.
我跟你说
Am I so famous
不会是我在辩论队的
in the debate team
名气太大了
that they recognize me?
认出我来了
That's her.
就是她
Today must be the day
一看今天就是个可以
that we gain worldwide fame.
一举成名的日子
Let's keep training.
让我们继续训练吧
Come on!
走起
Our team is going to train.
我们一队要训练了
Please leave.
请吧
What are
你那俩窟窿
your two eyes for?
长的是干嘛的
Can't you see the time?
看不着点啊
We have a competition tomorrow,
我们一队明天要比赛
which is very important,
很重要的那种
so we need to use this classroom now.
所以现在就要训练
We've agreed that
我们之前说好的
this room is used by us before 8 o'clock.
八点之前归我们用
All interpretation rights
一切解释权
belong to team one.
归一队所有啊
Calm down.
冷静
Let me handle this.
我来
Kids
孩子们
After we come out and
出来呼吸一下
breathe in the fragrance of nature,
大自然的芬芳
do you feel more comfortable?
有没有觉着心情舒畅啊
What happened to you guys?
怎么了这是
What wusses are we to leave there?
就这么出来   不   啊
Exactly.
就是
It's not like we can't beat them.
我们又不是打不过他们
Maybe we'll have a chance
大不了我们去跟老教练
to talk to the old coach.
一起叙叙旧嘛
Right.
没错
Can't you
你就不能再
hold on for a while?
坚持一会儿吗
Sa
小撒
At least we wait until Liu Yanze comes.
至少要等到刘彦泽来啊
Everybody,
大家
don't be so tit-for-tat.
别这么针锋相对的
After all, we are all school teams.
毕竟我们都是校队
This is not conducive to the construction
总这样
of both teams.
不利于两队建设
Look,
你看
Hao has a higher ideological consciousness.
还是小好觉悟高
We must not
我们现在
be disturbed
千万不要被这些
by these
外界因素
external factors.
所干扰
Our top priority now
我们现在的当务之急
is to win the next game.
是要拿下下一场比赛
As long as we win this game,
只要拿下这场比赛
we have the right to voice our opinions.
我们就有了话语权
In the next game,
下一场比赛
we'll have to face
我们要面临的
the legendary Fulin College
就是传说中
who is always performing well.
稳扎稳打的涪临学院
This team is very crazy
这支队伍很迷呀
and unpredictable.
实力深不可测
But they signed up for such a
但是他们却参加了这样
inferior competition,
末流的
Qiyi Cup College Students Debate Tournament,
秋奕杯大学生辩论赛
which is expected by no one.
那是谁都没有想到的
I bet
我打赌是
they slipped their hands when they signed up.
报名的时候手滑了
Yes.
嗯
I will venture one yuan on it.
我赌一块钱
I'll venture 1.5 yuan.
那我赌一块五吧
Well.
好了
Let's take a look at
那就让咱们来看一下
their lineup.
对方的阵容配置
Wang Wenjing, the first debater,
一辩 王文静
is called a live history book.
号称是行走的历史书
She has a clear logic,
逻辑清晰
and is very good at using historical evidences.
非常擅长历史佐证
She knows everything from poetry
上知诗词歌赋
to worldly wisdom.
下知人情世故
Her hobby is drilling wood to make fire,
爱好是钻木取火
and has won the Best Environmental Protection Award.
还曾荣获过最佳环保奖
Wow.
哇
She's so unique!
好有个性
Zhao Chengong, the second debater.
二辩 赵成功
he is best at using a straw man argument
最擅长偷换概念
and making fast attacks,
快速攻击
which always makes his opponents defenseless.
让对手防不胜防
He often misleads his opponents
经常把对手绕到
until they don't know
自己都不知道
what they're talking about.
自己在说什么
Ge Lin, the third debater.
三辩戈林
He is the school beau and good learner of Fulin college,
涪临校草 学霸男神级
and is best at finding subtle loopholes
最擅长在攻防之间
between attack and defense.
找到细微的漏洞
One Shot, One Kill.
一击必杀
He is known as
号称是
the direct disciple known as Socrates.
苏格拉底的嫡传弟子
Not bad.
是蛮帅的
But
不过
he's still far behind him.
还是差远了
I boycott school beau.
我抵制校草
I boycott him
我抵制
with no reason.
我就抵制
Gong Huaqing, the fourth debater.
四辩 龚华青
She has a wealth of knowledge
知识储备量非常丰富
and her arguments have a sense of substitution
她的辩词非常有代入感
and are easy to resonate.
很容易达到共鸣
She is the main figure in the sentimental school.
情感派主力人物
Let's have a look.
来 看一下
As my fellow debater said,
对方辩友所言
when the means
从手段上升为
are transformed to the purpose,
目的的时候
humans will be reduced
人就从主人沦落
from masters to slaves.
为了奴隶
They talk so fast.
他们这语速也太快了
When we finish our words,
等咱们说完
they are almost going to the award stage.
人都要颁奖了
So,
所以
it's very important to increase our speed of speaking.
加强语速很重要
And this is our goal for the next stage.
这也就是咱们的下一步
Improve our ability of oral expression.
练口条
Practicing language
现在这语言形式范儿
has long been outdated.
早就过气了
Now we all pursue
咱现在都
the quality of the content, OK?
追求内容好不好
That's just one thought.
那只是一家之词
Actually,
其实我觉得
I think this is very meaningful.
这个挺有意思的
Debate is not just
辩论它不只是考逻辑
a test of logic and knowledge.
和这个知识储备
If your expression level
如果你的口条
is the same as
和声音条件
the top host's,
都跟一线主持人一样
isn't it pleasing to the audience's ears?
那多赏心悦目啊
Don't you think so?
对吧
A nice point.
说得好
And some small training
而且只是一些小训练
can be done when you chat, quarrel,
平时在你们唠嗑 吵架
sing Karaoke, practice rap music,
唱K 练说唱音乐
and even go to the bathroom.
上厕所的时候
You can practice it everywhere.
都可以练一练
A famous professor
一位著名的
of the Line major
戏剧学院台词教授
at the drama college
曾经这样告诉我们
once told us that
台词是在生活当中
lines are practiced in life.
练出来的
So, we should integrate line practice into life.
所以说要融入生活嘛
Okay, let's stop here.
好了 闲言少叙
Go into action, everybody.
孩儿们 给爷操练起来
What do you want?
干什么
Come here, come here.
过来过来过来
Sit down.
坐
What's wrong?
干什么
When did you start?
什么时候开始的
What's going on?
到底发展到什么情况了
What?
什么
I don't know...  Yu, Yu, Yu.
不是我 鱼 鱼 鱼
The photos of you and Nan Bei have been exposed.
你跟南北的图被曝光了
What photos do we have?
我跟南北有什么图
Look!
你看
Is this a photo of you and Nan Bei?
这是不是你跟南北
It updates every day.
每日都更新的